Guide to the John Casper Branner Papers SC0034
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Correspondence, Series 1
  - Letters In E - G, 1912 (Box 45, Folder 221)
  - Letters In H, 1912 (Box 45, Folder 222)
  - Letters In I - L, 1912 (Box 46, Folder 223)
  - Letters In M, 1912 (Box 46, Folder 224)
  - Letters In N - Q, 1912 (Box 46, Folder 225)
  - Letters In R - S, 1912 (Box 46, Folder 226)
  - Letters In S, 1912 (Box 46, Folder 227)
  - Letters In T - Z, 1912 (Box 47, Folder 228)
  - Letters In A, 1913 (Box 47, Folder 229)
  - Report to Board of Trustees in re Medical School. (Box 47, Folder 230)
  - Letters In B, 1913 (Box 47, Folder 231)
  - Letters In C, 1913 (Box 47, Folder 232)
  - Letters In D - F, 1913 (Box 47, Folder 233)
  - Letters In G - H, 1913 (Box 47, Folder 234)
  - Letters In I - L, 1913 (Box 48, Folder 235)
    Of note: David S. Jordan to Branner upon turning the presidency of Stanford over to him.
  - Letters In M, 1913 (Box 48, Folder 236)
  - Letters In N - P, 1913 (Box 48, Folder 237)
  - Letters In R - S, 1913 (Box 48, Folder 238)
  - Letters In S, 1913 (Box 48, Folder 239)
  - Letters In T - V, 1913 (Box 48, Folder 240)
  - Letters In U - Z, 1913 (Box 49, Folder 241)
  - Letters In A, 1914 (Box 49, Folder 242)
  - Letters In B, 1914 (Box 49, Folder 243)
  - Letters In C, 1914 (Box 49, Folder 244)
  - Letters In D - F, 1914 (Box 49, Folder 245)
  - Letters In G - H, 1914 (Box 50, Folder 246)
  - Letters In I - J, 1914 (Box 50, Folder 247)
  - Letters In K - L, 1914 (Box 50, Folder 248)
    Of note: Charles F. Lummis regarding Dr. Fleugel's death; personal letters.
  - Letters In M - O, 1914 (Box 50, Folder 249)
  - Letters In P - R, 1914 (Box 50, Folder 250)
  - Letters In S, 1914 (Box 51, Folder 251)
  - Letters In T - Z, 1914 (Box 51, Folder 252)
  - Letters In A - B, 1915 (Box 51, Folder 253)
  - Letters In B, 1915 (Box 51, Folder 254)
  - Letters In C, 1915 (Box 51, Folder 255)
  - Letters In D - F, 1915 (Box 52, Folder 256)
  - Letters In G - H, 1915 (Box 52, Folder 257)
  - Letters In I - L, 1915 (Box 52, Folder 258)
  - Letters In M - O, 1915 (Box 52, Folder 259)
  - Letters In P, 1915 (Box 53, Folder 260)
  - Letters In R - S, 1915 (Box 53, Folder 261)
  - Letters In T -Z, 1915 (Box 53, Folder 262)
    Of note: Woodrow Wilson thanking Branner for his suggestion for controlling slides in the Panama Canal.
  - Letters In A, 1916 (Box 53, Folder 263)
  - Letters In B, 1916 (Box 53, Folder 264)
  - Letters In C - E, 1916 (Box 54, Folder 265)
  - Letters In F - G, 1916 (Box 54, Folder 266)
  - Letters In H, 1916 (Box 54, Folder 267)
  - Letters In J, 1916 (Box 54, Folder 268)
  - Letters In K - L, 1916 (Box 54, Folder 269)
  - Letters In M - P, 1916 (Box 54, Folder 270)
  - Letters In R - S, 1916 (Box 55, Folder 271)
  - Letters In S - V, 1916 (Box 55, Folder 272)
  - Letters In W - Z, 1916 (Box 55, Folder 273)
  - Letters In A - B, 1917 (Box 55, Folder 274)
  - Letters In B, 1917 (Box 55, Folder 275)
  - Letters In C - F, 1917 (Box 56, Folder 276)
  - Letters In G - I, 1917 (Box 56, Folder 277)
  - Letters In J - L, 1917 (Box 56, Folder 278)
  - Letters In M - P, 1917 (Box 56, Folder 279)
  - Letters In R - S, 1917 (Box 57, Folder 280)
  - Letters In T - Z, 1917 (Box 57, Folder 281)
  - Letters In A - B, 1918 (Box 57, Folder 282)
  - Letters In C - F, 1918 (Box 57, Folder 283)
  - Letters In G - L, 1918 (Box 58, Folder 284)
  - Letters In M - R, 1918 (Box 58, Folder 285)
  - Letters In S - Z, 1918 (Box 58, Folder 286)
  - Letters In A - B, 1919 (Box 58, Folder 287)
  - Letters In C - F, 1919 (Box 58, Folder 288)
  - Letters In G - I, 1919 (Box 59, Folder 289)
  - Letters In J - L, 1919 (Box 59, Folder 290)
  - Letters In M - R, 1919 (Box 59, Folder 291)
  - Letters In S - V, 1919 (Box 59, Folder 292)
  - Letters In W - Z, 1919 (Box 59, Folder 293)
  - Letters In A - B, 1920 (Box 60, Folder 294)
  - Letters In C - F, 1920 (Box 60, Folder 295)
  - Letters In G - H, 1920 (Box 60, Folder 296)
  - Letters In J - I, 1920 (Box 60, Folder 297)
  - Letters In M - O, 1920 (Box 61, Folder 298)
  - Letters In P - S, 1920 (Box 61, Folder 299)
  - Letters In T - W, 1920 (Box 61, Folder 300)
  - Letters In W - Z, 1920 (Box 61, Folder 301)
  - Letters out, carbons, 1920-1921 (Box 61, Folder 302)
  - Notes, etc, 1916, 1920 (Box 61, Folder 303)
  - Letters In, A - B, 1921 (Box 62, Folder 304)
  - Letters In, C - H, 1921 (Box 62, Folder 305)
  - Letters In, J - O, 1921 (Box 62, Folder 306)
  - Letters In, P - V, 1921 (Box 62, Folder 307)
  - Letters In, W - Z, 1921 (Box 62, Folder 308)
- Manuscripts, drawings, clippings, photographs and maps, Series 2
  - Notes and manuscripts on Brazil, 1882 -1907 (Box 63a, Folder 309)
  - Correspondence, notes, photographs re Brazilian pottery, 1885 -1887 (Box 63a, Folder 309a)
  - Manuscript of Dr. Miguel Lisboa, translated by J. C. Branner (Box 63a, Folder 310)
  - Manuscript of Dr. Miguel Lisboa, translated by J. C. Branner, continued (Box 63a, Folder 311)
  - Brazil drawings. Some original drawings, most are line copies of photographs. (Box 63b, Folder 312)
  - Manuscript on the elevation and depression of the northeast coast of Brazil. (Box 63b, Folder 313)
  - Manuscript on the economic geology of the diamond bearing highlands of the state of Bahia, Brazil. (Box 63b, Folder 314)
  - Portuguese folksongs collected by Mrs. Waring. Joaquin Nabuco. O Dever dos monarchistas. With notes written by the author addressed to J. C. Branner, 1886 May (Box 63b, Folder 315)
  - Card file bibilography of works about Brazil. (Box 63c)
  - Notes of Roderick Crandall on the geology of Brazil, 1907 (Box 64, Folder 316)
  - Mining laws of Brazil. Translated from Portuguese by J. C. Branner, July 1920 (Box 64, Folder 317)
  - Bibliography on the geology of Brazil (bound typescript) (Box 64, Folder 317a)
  - Brazilian textbook of Geology: manuscript (Box 64, Folder 318)
  - Brazilian textbook of Geology: manuscript (Box 64, Folder 319)
  - Geologia Elementar: manuscript of the 2nd Edition (Box 64, Folder 320)
  - Geologia Elementar: manuscript of the 2nd Edition (Box 64, Folder 321)
  - Geologia Elementar: manuscript of the 2nd Edition (Box 64, Folder 322)
  - Correspondence regarding Stanford University establishing an Eucalyptus farm. (Box 65a, Folder 323)
  - Articles: (Box 65a, Folder 323a)
    - The Study of Science.
    - The San Francisco earthquake from the geologists point of view, J. C. Branner, May 1906
    - An early discovery of fullers' earth in Arkansas by J. C. Branner, Feb., 1912
    - Alexis Perrey: a bit of seismologic history, by Count Montessus de Palloe. Translated by J. C. Branner, March, 1913
    - The Tejon pass eartquake by J. C. Branner, Oct. 1916
  - Earthquake clippings, 1920 -1921 (Box 65a, Folder 324)
  - Scrapbook of clippings on San Francisco, 1906 (Box 65a, Folder 324a)
  - The Seismological work of John Milne. Manuscript (Box 65a, Folder 325)
  - Report for Spring Valley Water Company. (Box 65a, Folder 326)
  - Installation as president of L. S. J. U., Address, newspaper article, program, invitation of Board of Trustees., Oct. 1, 1913 (Box 65a, Folder 326a)
  - Committee to investigate Panama Canal slides, Correspondence, minutes, report., 1915-1916 (Box 65a, Folder 327)
  - Miscellaneous obituaries of Mrs. Branner. (Box 65b, Folder 328)
  - Early Days at Stanford by Mrs. Branner. (Box 65b, Folder 328a)
  - Baker genealogy. (Box 65b, Folder 329)
  - Penrose, R. A. F, Jr. (Box 65b, Folder 330)
  - Penrose, R. A. F, Jr. Biographical Memoirs, National Academy of Sciences, v. 21, Memorial, reprinted from Bulletin of the Geological Society of America, v. 36, pp. 15-44. Articles on Branner's library., 1927; March 30, 1925 (Box 65b, Folder 330)
  - Arkansas photographs (Box 66, Folder 331)
  - Glass slides of Drake's relief map of California (Box 66, Folder 332)
  - Geologic maps of Brazil. Plates, cuts. (Box 66, Folder 333)
  - Geology of South America. Photographs, cuts, clippings. (Box 66, Folder 334)
  - Geology of Brazil. Photographs, maps, and plates. (Box 66, Folder 335)
  - Engravings from photographs of Brazil and Yosemite. (Box 66, Folder 336)
  - Photographs of South America (Box 67, Folder 337)
  - Photographs of South America (Box 67, Folder 338)
  - Photographs of South America. Geology (Box 67, Folder 339)
  - Photograph albums of various trips to Brazil, not labeled or dated, circa 1890-1916 (Box 68, Folder 340)
  - Photograph album, Brazil, Summer 1899 (Box 68, Folder 341)
  - Photograph album, Brazil, Summer 1899 (Box 68, Folder 342)
  - Photograph album, Brazil, Summer 1913 (Box 68, Folder 343)
  - F. L. Garrison, photographer. States of Bahia and Minas Geraes, Brazil, 1916 (Box 68, Folder 344)
  - Scrapbooks of photographs of the April 18, 1906 earthquake, compiled by J. C. Branner. 2 v. (Box 69, Folder 345)
  - Scrapbooks of photographs of the April 18, 1906 earthquake, compiled by J. C. Branner. 2 v. (Box 69, Folder 346)
  - Photographs illustrating the effects of the earthquake of April 18, 1906. Mostly made under the direction of J. C. Branner. (Box 70)
  - Field notebooks. Included are the notebooks of Branner and his students on the April 18, 1906 earthquake, the earthquake investigation of 1917, Branner's personal field notes on Brazil, U.S.G.S. Field Section books, and the Stanford Expedition to Brazil, 1876, 1887, 1903 and 1910, 1911 (Box 71)
  - Scrapbook of earthquake clippings. Vol 1. Vol. 2, 1910-1915, 1915-1922 (Box 76)
  - Scrapbooks on the geology of Brazil. 2 vols., 1907- (Box 83)
  - Autograph books (2 volumes): miscellaneous autographs, autographs of geologists. (Box 90)
  - Geologic map of Brazil. Reprinted from the Bulletin of the Geological Society of America., 1919 (Box 92)
  - Map of geology about the mouth of the Rio Amazonas; after Katzer; Sketch map of the approximate limestone areas of the interior of Bahia, Brazil; Sketch map of parts of Alaogoas and Pernambuco, Brazil (Box 94 os)
- Articles, Series 3
  - List of the more important publications of J. C. Branner, List of books, pamphlets and maps in the library of J. C. Branner., 1884-1902 (Box 72, Folder 347)
  - Articles of Notes of lectures on botany included., 1883-1886 (Box 72, Folder 348)
  - Articles of, 1887-1890 (Box 72, Folder 349)
  - Articles of, 1891-1895 (Box 72, Folder 350)
  - Articles of, 1896-1897 (Box 72, Folder 351)
  - Articles of, 1898-1901 (Box 73, Folder 352)
  - Articles of, 1902-1905 (Box 73, Folder 353)
  - Articles of, 1906-1908 (Box 73, Folder 354)
  - Articles of, 1909-1911 (Box 73, Folder 355)
  - Articles of, 1912-1915 (Box 74, Folder 356)
  - Articles of, 1916-1917, 1919 (Box 74, Folder 357)
  - Articles of and Memorials., 1920, 1921 (Box 74, Folder 358)
- Books by J. C. Branner, Series 4
  - List of graduates in geology and mining, Stanford University [1892-1920] (Box 75)
  - How and Why Stories., 1921 (Box 77)
  - Observations made upon the Arkansas River., 1887-1888 (Box 78)
  - J. C. Branner and J. F. Newsom. The Phosphate Rocks of Arkansas. Bulletin 74. Arkansas Agricultural Experiment Station., 1902 (Box 79)
  - A Bibliography of clays and the ceramic arts. Columbus, Ohio, 1906 (Box 80)
  - Multiple Volumes: (Box 81)
    - A Bibliography of the geology, mineralogy and paleontology of Brazil. Rio de Janeiro, 1903; 2 copies
    - A Bibliography of the geology, mineralogy and paleontology of Brazil.
    - A geologia cretacea e terciaria da Bacio do Brazil. Sergipe-Alaquoas., 1899
    - Geologia Elementar. Rio de Janeiro., 1906; 2 copies
    - Geologia Elementar. 2nd edition. Rio de Janeiro., 1915
    - Papers on Brazil., 1887-1893
  - Multiple Volumes: (Box 82)
    - J. C. Branner, translator. Constitutions of Brazil., 1894
    - The Stone reefs of Brazil, their geological and geographical relations, with a chapter on the coral reefs. Bulletin of the Museum of Comparative Zoology of Harvard College. V. 44. Cambridge, MA. 1904., 1894; 2 copies
  - Multiple Volumes: (Box 84)
    - Decomposition of rocks in Brazil. Bulletin of the Geological Society of America, v. 7, pp. 255-314, Feb. 1896
    - The Crastaceous and Tertiary Geolgoy of the Sergipe-Alagoas Basin of Brazil. Transactions of the Am. Philosophical Society, XVI., (1899); 3 copies
    - Catalogue of the Brazilian Library of J. C. Branner.
  - Multiple Volumes: (Box 85)
    - Portuguese Grammar. New York, 1910
    - Portuguese Grammar. New York, 2nd. Ed., 1914
    - J. C. Branner, translator. History of the origin and establishment of the inquisition in Portugal. Stanford University, CA, 1926
    - Syllabus of Elementary Geology. Stanford University, 1898; 3 copies
  - Syllabus of Elementary Geology. 2nd ed. Stanford University, 1902; Five copies; copy 5 includes notes by Ada Devendorf from 1906 class. (Box 86)
  - Multiple Volumes: (Box 87)
    - Syllabus of Elementary Geology. 3rd. ed. Stanford University, 1908; 3 copies
    - J. C. Branner and John F. Newsom. Syllabus of Economic Geology. Stanford University, (annotated)., 1895
  - Multiple Volumes: (Box 88)
    - J. C. Branner and John F. Newsom. Syllabus of Economic Geology. 2nd. Ed. Stanford University, 1900; 2 copies
    - J. C. Branner and John F. Newsom. Syllabus of Economic Geology. 3rd. Ed. Stanford University, 1911; 2 copies
  - J. C. Branner, director. The Papers of the Stanford Expedition to Brazil in 1911. Vol. I, 1914; 2 copies (Box 89)
  - Casper Branner of Virginia and His Descendants. Privately printed, Stanford University, CA, 1913 (Box 91)
  - Casper Branner of Virginia and His Descendants [microfilm], 2 microfilm reel(s) (Box 92)
  - Syllabus of Elementary Geology. 4th. ed. Stanford University, 1912 (Box 93)
- Revolution in Brazil, Series 5
  - Revolution in Brazil: newspaper clippings, 1889-1893 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Revolution in Brazil: newspaper clippings, 1884-1896 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Revolution in Brazil: newspaper clippings, 1883-1903 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Revolution in Brazil: magazine articles, 1893-1894 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Revolution in Brazil: manuscript notes (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Revolution in Brazil: manuscript drafts (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Additional papers, 1885-1925; Accession 2011-062; 0.25 Linear Feet
  - Letters by Branner to Miguel A. R. Lisboa (in Portuguese), 1915 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Orville A. Derby correspondence with Branner, Herbert Killburn Scott, and others pertaining to work in Brazil, 1893-1901 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Reprints by Branner, 1885-1920 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Reprints by other authors, 1907-1025 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Maps: Caminhamento entre Pouso dos Macacos e Aldeia Queimada and Caminhamento entre Salto do Rio Sepotuba e Porto dos Bugres, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Maps: Geologia da linna Caceres ao Rio Sangrador Grande [undated] and Geologia de una partie do estado de Matto-Grosso, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 6)